<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>endurance sport | Manuel Revilla, DVM, PhD</title>
    <link>/categories/endurance-sport/</link>
      <atom:link href="/categories/endurance-sport/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>endurance sport</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Last updated Mar. 21, 2020 &amp;#183; © 2019 Manuel Revilla under (CC BY-SA 4.0)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>endurance sport</title>
      <link>/categories/endurance-sport/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cycling at France</title>
      <link>/post/20200330_cyclingatfrance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/20200330_cyclingatfrance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you have arrived here searching for something, maybe it is because you, like me, love endurance sports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I am going to talk about other of my passion, road cycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does not matter if you consider yourself a climber, or sprinter, or even an occasionaly rider who wants to know more about your surroundings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My passion to cycling came to me in 2014, motivated for an old childhood friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since that year until now I have had the chance to ride in some countries, and climb some of the most iconic and rewarding climbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I want to show you the climbs I have made in my current country of residence, France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many riders France is pretty much consider the king of pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The home of the &lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;Tour de France&amp;rdquo;&lt;/i&gt; is one of the best places in the world to pit yourself against gravity in pursuit of sporting greatness, unbeatable views, and utter exhaustion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some you will have heard of but never attempted, some offer a fresh perspective on legendary ascents, and others are simply the stuff of cyclists&amp;rsquo; nightmares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you are looking to add a few rides to your bucket list, this plot can help you to find your perfect ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find from legendary climbs consider true icons, to others that are not very know, but equally hard and beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before check the plot, some aspect should be highlight:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&amp;middot; 1. DEGREE OF DIFFICULTY &amp;middot;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number associated to each climb represent the degree of difficulty, the bigger the number the bigger the difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This degree is based on the formula given by Juanto Uribarri. A complete description, in Spanish, could be find in this post at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.altimetrias.net/articulos/4cd.asp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Altimetrias&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could be a good estimator to compare the difficulty of different climbs, at least from an objective point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this, the climbs are classified in four categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: square&#34;&gt;
     &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
         &lt;strong&gt;HC&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;i&gt;Hors cat&amp;eacute;gorie&lt;/i&gt;, french term to designate a climb that is &#34;beyond categorization&#34;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Category 1&lt;/strong&gt; 120-240
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
       &lt;strong&gt;Category 2&lt;/strong&gt; 60-119
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
       &lt;strong&gt;Category 3&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;60
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;-1&#34;&gt;
* Note that in professional cycling stage races such as, &lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;Tour de France&amp;rdquo;&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;Giro d&amp;rsquo;Italia&amp;rdquo;&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vuelta a Espa&amp;ntilde;a&amp;rdquo;&lt;/i&gt;, this classification differs depending of the organization decision.
&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an easy display, only climbings belonging to HC, first and second category are represented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&amp;middot; 2. MORE THAN ONE DEGREE OF DIFFICULTY FOR AN SPECIFIC CLIMB &amp;middot;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many of the climbs, you have several roads to get to the top. For those cases, the side used is specified and its degree of difficulty indicated as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&amp;middot; 3. COMPLETE INFORMATION FOR THE CLIMB &amp;middot;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reveal more information for a specific climb, click on the associated point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The associated information included the length (km), average gradient (%), maximum gradient (%), cumulative elevation gain (m), and the height of the climb (m).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe title=&#34;Cycling climb locations in Andorra and France&#34; aria-label=&#34;Locator maps&#34; id=&#34;datawrapper-chart-RTuBK&#34; src=&#34;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/RTuBK/9/&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&#34; height=&#34;509&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;!function(){&amp;ldquo;use strict&amp;rdquo;;window.addEventListener(&amp;ldquo;message&amp;rdquo;,function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&amp;ldquo;datawrapper-height&amp;rdquo;])for(var e in a.data[&amp;ldquo;datawrapper-height&amp;rdquo;]){var t=document.getElementById(&amp;ldquo;datawrapper-chart-&amp;rdquo;+e)||document.querySelector(&amp;ldquo;iframe[src*=&amp;lsquo;&amp;ldquo;+e+&amp;rdquo;&amp;rsquo;]&amp;ldquo;);t&amp;amp;&amp;amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&amp;ldquo;datawrapper-height&amp;rdquo;][e]+&amp;ldquo;px&amp;rdquo;)}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Click on location to reveal more information &amp;brvbar; Updated 2019/11/01 &lt;br&gt;
Map: &amp;copy; OpenStreetMap contributors &amp;middot; Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.altimetrias.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;APM | Altimetrias&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you find this post useful and interesting, and if you decide to ride in one of the detailed climbs I am sure it is going to give you the biggest sense of achievement ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
&#34;Those who ride a bicycle know that in life nothing is really flat.&#34; 
  &lt;/p&gt;
-Ren&amp;egrave; Fallet
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amateur marathoner</title>
      <link>/post/20191213_amateur/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/20191213_amateur/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Amateur is a word taken from French, that was present in that language since the XV century, after replacing the popular form &lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;amaor&amp;rdquo;&lt;/i&gt;, which derives from the Latin &lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;amator&amp;rdquo;&lt;/i&gt; meaning &amp;ldquo;who loves&amp;rdquo;.
Then in the XVIII century it was given a modern meaning alluding to one who practises a science, art, sport&amp;hellip; without the need to be professional for it, but it was not until the XIX century that the amateur word was implemented as a sporting term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For myself, I honor the amateur spirit upon which the sport was founded and champion the Running Class - the non-professional yet competitive runners dedicated to the pursuit of personal excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who knows me will know that one of my passions are endurance sports, with specially attention to marathons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe in competition and the meritocracy of racing. Not because winning and losing are particularly important, but because competition sends us on an innately human journey. A large part of training for a marathon is learning from your mistakes. Runners must listen to their bodies and decide when to train, and when not to train, based on how they cope will all they put the body through. The profound physical and mental demands of training and racing lead to a richer and more sensitive and thrilling life. In my experience, I&amp;rsquo;ve gained a lot of humility and perseverance for completing the marathon distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I usually combine this passion with other of my hobbies, meet new landscapes and communities&amp;hellip; I consider that traveling cross-world is a fulfilling way to enhance each marathon experience. It has led me to participate in several marathons around the world, trying to improve, in each one of my participations, my personal record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last April 15 I set my personal best time in the Boston Marathon, my first Major. For those who are not familiar with this term, a Major is the conversational style to call a marathon which belongs to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.worldmarathonmajors.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Abbott World Marathon Majors&lt;/a&gt;. A series consisting of six of the largest and most renowned marathons in the world. The races take place in Tokyo, Boston, London, Berlin, Chicago and New York City.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t be happier about my first participation in a Major, because I broke my &lt;strong&gt;personal record&lt;/strong&gt;, setting up a finishing time of &lt;strong&gt;02h48&amp;rsquo;23&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, which represent a pace of &lt;strong&gt;3&amp;rsquo;59&amp;rdquo;/km (15.04 km/h)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this plot you can find all my participations and my personal progression in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pheidippides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Philippides&lt;/a&gt; (&amp;Phi;&amp;iota;&amp;lambda;&amp;iota;&amp;pi;&amp;pi;&amp;iacute;&amp;delta;&amp;eta;&amp;sigmaf;) distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/RScatterPlot_MarathonParticipations.png&#34; alt=&#34;This is an image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to dive into my personal marathon participation statistics I invite you to check this summary table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/RTablePlot_MarathonParticipations.png&#34; alt=&#34;This is an image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, in the following tables you can see the all-time top-5 marathoners (men and women), which reflects that human beings have no limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/RTablePlotAthletes_Men_Marathon.png&#34; alt=&#34;This is an image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/RTablePlotAthletes_Women_Marathon.png&#34; alt=&#34;This is an image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.worldathletics.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;World Athletics&lt;/a&gt; (before International Association of Athletics Federations, IAAF)
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each of my training programs for the marathon I take notes that help me improve my performance, as well as embody my personal experiences. Remembering the notes I usually take, the plots shown in this post are made using the R package &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=xkcd&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;xkcd&lt;/a&gt;, which represents the traces of handwriting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, I want to share with you this quote of &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/borntorunhiddent00mcdo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Born to Run: A Hidden Tribe, Superathletes, and the Greatest Race the World Has Never Seen&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; book, a must to be read if you want to be consider as a marathoner:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
&#34;Every morning in Africa, a gazelle wakes up, it knows it must outrun the fastest lion or it will be killed. 
Every morning in Africa, a lion wakes up. 
It knows it must run faster than the slowest gazelle, or it will starve. 
It doesn&#39;t matter whether you&#39;re the lion or a gazelle-when the sun comes up, you&#39;d better be running.&#34; 
  &lt;/p&gt;
-Christopher McDougall
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
